{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This war included the first U.S. use of the terms \"D-day\" and \"H-hour\" in military combat at Saint-Mihiel [[SANH-mee-HYEL]]. Omar Bundy helped lead men in this war at a battle at which Lloyd Williams quipped, \"Retreat? Hell, we just got here.\" The pigeon Cher Ami [[SHEHR ah-MEE]] helped save the Lost Battalion in this war during the Battle of the Argonne Forest. The idea of the Devil Dog came from this war's Battle of Belleau Wood. The Harlem Hellfighters fought in, for ten points, what \"war to end all wars\"?",
      "answer": [
        "World War One or First World War",
        "the Great War"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "An 1802 James Gilray cartoon protesting the use of these things depicted the \"Cow Pock,\" with cows emerging from people's bodies. The first one of these things was made using sores that appeared on the hands of milkmaids. Recent examples of these things utilize mRNA to program cells to produce a certain \"spike protein.\" Jonas Salk is best known for developing an inactivated one of these things to fight polio. For ten points, name these things which are typically injected to prevent a patient from contracting a disease.",
      "answer": [
        "Vaccine",
        "Inoculation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Ferdinand Lot questioned whether this man actually defeated 430 thousand enemy soldiers, though Ernest Desjardins [[day-zhar-DAH]] credited that number to a transcription error. Aulus Hirtius [[OW-luss HEAR-shus]] wrote the eighth book of one of this man's works which features Vorenus and Pullo. A work by this man describes his defeat of Vercingetorix [[VEHR-sin-GET-or-rix]], and this man wrote Commentaries on the Gallic Wars. Known for crossing the Rubicon, for ten points, who was this Roman who was killed on the Ides of March?",
      "answer": "Gaius Julius Caesar"
    },
    {
      "question": "Herman Melville's novel The Confidence-Man depicts travelers telling stories along this body of water. In one novel, a pair of con artists traveling on this body of water pretend to be King Louis XVII and the Duke of Nonesuch [[NUN-such]]. A memoir titled Life on [this body of water] was written by Mark Twain, who set many of his novels along this waterway. For ten points, name this long U.S. river, on which Jim and Huckleberry Finn float in a raft.",
      "answer": "Mississippi River 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "The annexation of what is now this state was facilitated under the Newlands Resolution during the William McKinley administration. This state was formerly a Republic which was led by Sanford Dole. Sugarcane planters overthrew this modern day state’s native ruler, Queen Liliʻuokalani [[lee-lee-woh-kah-LUH-nee]]. For ten points, name this state in which an attack on a base which included Battleship Row served as a precursor to U.S. entry into World War Two.",
      "answer": [
        "Hawai'i",
        "Kingdom of Hawai'i",
        "Republic of Hawai'i",
        "Territory of Hawai'i"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The creator of this game series founded MicroProse in 1982, which produced products such as an historically-based game which allowed players to sail the Spanish Main as a pirate. In the 2016 release from this series, players can reveal the Hermetic Order secret society by discovering a natural wonder. That game in this series also includes a civics tree to parallel its technology tree and features novel playable factions such as the Scythians and the Hungarians. For ten points, name this strategic computer game series whose entries bear the name of creator Sid Meier.",
      "answer": [
        "Sid Meier's Civilization",
        "Sid Meier’s Civilization VI"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This region was home to three confederacies, together known as the Samhan, who fought against Qin Kai [[CHIN KAI]] and the Yan. Wei Man invaded this region to end a dynasty supposedly founded by Dangun and a mythical bear-woman. Four Han Commanderies, including Leland and Lintun, were set up after this region's state of Gojoseon [[GOH-joh-sun]] was captured. This region's three kingdoms were Baekje [[BECK- jeh]], Goguryeo [[GOH-guhr-yuh]], and Silla. For ten points, name this peninsula which today includes a country led by Kim Jong Un.",
      "answer": "Korean Peninsula"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man was born in what is today Algeria and wrote one of the first autobiographies in Western literature in which he relates his sinful early life and the tireless efforts of his mother, Monica, to save his soul. As a young man in Carthage, this future theologian was enamored of Manichaeism [[man-ih-KEE-ism]], the belief in an eternal conflict between light and darkness. In Milan, this man met Saint Ambrose, who eventually baptized him into the Catholic church. For ten points, what saint and Bishop of Hippo wrote the Confessions?",
      "answer": "Saint Augustine of Hippo 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "question": "Two answers required. A coalition led by these two cities lost to the strategos Epaminondas [[ee-pam-ih-NON-dahs]] at the Battle of Mantinea under the leadership of a king of the Eurypontid dynasty. One of these cities tore down the other’s “Long Wall” which reached Piraeus [[pie-RAY-us]], and these two states signed the \"fifty year\" Peace of Nicias. Admiral Lysander from one of these cities sank the other city’s Delian fleet during the Battle of Aegospotami [[ay-goh-SPOH-tah-mai]]. For ten points, name these two Greek poleis [[POH-lice]] which fought each other in the Peloponnesian War.",
      "answer": [
        "Athens and Sparta",
        "in either order"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this state, market manipulation and megawatt laundering by traders under false names like “Death Star” and “Red Congo” led to rolling blackouts during the late 1990s and early 2000s. The murder of 15-year old Latasha Harlins by Soon Ja Du was one of the factors that increased racial tensions and led to the 1992 riots in this state. The successful recall of this state’s governor, Gray Davis, in 2003 led to the eventual election of actor Arnold Schwarzenegger. For ten points, name this state with the cities of Sacramento and Los Angeles.",
      "answer": "California 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Rupert of Wittelsbach [[VITT-els-BACH]], \"the Gentle\", was bankrolled by this city, whose aristocrats were targeted by its Ordinances of Justice. Bankers from this city were ruined when Edward III refused to pay his debts. \"The 8 Saints\" supported guildless artisans in this city's Ciompi [[CHOM-pee]] Revolt. This city became a republic after it rebelled following the death of Matilda of Tuscany. Housing art galleries such as the Uffizi, for ten points, name this major Italian city once led by the Medici family.",
        "answer": [
          "Florence",
          "Firenze",
          "Fiorentino"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "A piazza in Florence was named for this first King of Italy who was served by Camillo Benso, the Count of Cavour.",
        "answer": "Victor Emmanuel II"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Abram Joseph Ryan was considered the \"Poet-Priest\" of one side of this war for poems like \"The Conquered Banner.\" Allen Tate wrote a modernist poem as an “Ode” to this war’s dead, told by a narrator in a graveyard on an \"Ambitious November.” Ambrose Bierce’s experiences during this war inspired his short story “Chickamauga.” Jim Conklin dies from blood loss in an engagement in this war, causing Henry Fleming to flee the battlefield. For ten points, name this war depicted in The Red Badge of Courage.",
        "answer": "American Civil War"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "“Ode to the Confederate Dead” inspired this poet to write \"For the Union Dead,\" which is set in Boston Common. He also wrote \"The Quaker Graveyard in Nantucket.\"",
        "answer": "Robert Lowell"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Albert Toven and Randy Lawrence discovered aluminum versions of these objects which had been released in 1974, but were told they were government property. A large version of these objects included Wreath, Flowing Hair, and Draped Bust variants. Victor Brenner designed the Wheat stalk variety of these objects, many of which depict Abraham Lincoln. Made of zinc and copper, it is debated whether these coins are still necessary. For ten points, name this smallest denomination of U.S. coinage.",
        "answer": "U.S. Penny"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Lincoln Penny first appeared in 1909, having been ordered on the way out of office by this Republican president who considered himself to be Lincoln's political heir.",
        "answer": "Theodore \"Teddy\" Roosevelt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Several iterations of this entity were criticized for being political statements against the Bush Administration. A member of the Swedish parliament nominated Adolf Hitler for one of these in 1939. In 2010, a Chinese group created a competitor to this prize named for Confucius as a response to one of these being given to Liu Xiaobo [[LOO SHAO-BOH]]. First given to Henri Dunant [[doo-NANH]] and Frédéric Passy in 1901, for ten points, what is this award, one of five established in the will of a Swedish industrialist?",
        "answer": "Nobel Peace Prize"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This organization, the food-assistance branch of the U.N., was awarded the Nobel Peace Prize in 2020 for its efforts to feed those affected by conflict.",
        "answer": [
          "World Food Programme",
          "WFP"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One work dictated by this man was partially lost by his neighbor, Martin Harris, and was allegedly verified in the presence of the Three Witnesses. Religious communities established by this man included those in Kirtland and Independence. This man was murdered by a mob after he ordered the destruction of a printing press for the Expositor. This man claimed to have been given two golden plates containing sacred texts by the angel Moroni. For ten points, name this founder of the Mormon Church.",
        "answer": "Joseph Smith, Jr."
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Smith was murdered while in a jail cell in this state's city of Carthage. Smith had also gained control of the government of this state's nearby city of Nauvoo.",
        "answer": "Illinois"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Confederate sympathizers from this nation led by Vernon Guyon Locke captured and commandeered a Union steamer in the Chesapeake Affair. Rebels from this nation entered U.S. waters while aboard the Caroline, which was later burned by British forces. The death of General Richard Montgomery occurred during an invasion of this nation, leading to Benedict Arnold taking over and heading an ineffectual siege of Quebec City. For ten points, name this northern neighbor of the United States.",
        "answer": "Canada"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Caroline Affair occurred on this river which forms part of the border between Ontario and New York.",
        "answer": "Niagara River 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Defenders secret society operated on this island, losing the Battle of the Diamond. The Battle of Vinegar Hill took place near Wexford during a French-supported rebellion on this island led by Wolfe Tone. This island's lands were concentrated in Protestant hands in the Ascendency. Charles Parnell led a home-rule movement on this island, whose oldest surviving university is Trinity College. For ten points, what island contains a Republic with its capital at Dublin?",
        "answer": [
          "Ireland",
          "Eire"
        ]
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Vinegar Hill was depicted in the poem \"Requiem for the Croppies,\" written by this Irish author of Death of a Naturalist and winner of the 1995 Nobel Prize in Literature.",
        "answer": "Seamus Heaney"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Antonio Gramsci referred to this philosophy as the \"philosophy of praxis\" in his Prison Notebooks while imprisoned by Italy's Fascist regime. With Arnold Ruge [[ROO-guh]], this philosophy's namesake led the newspaper the German-French Annals. Lesser known books by this philosophy's namesake include Grundrisse and The German Ideology. Espoused by the Maoist and Bolshevik parties, for ten points, what is this communist philosophy named after the author of Das Kapital?",
        "answer": "Marxism"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Marxist philosopher outlined his namesake philosophy in books such as The State and Revolution and Imperialism: the Highest Stage of Capitalism. This revolutionary also issued ten directives in his \"April Theses.\"",
        "answer": [
          "Vladimir Ilyich Lenin",
          "Vladimire Ilyich Ulyanov"
        ]
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Presidential Inaugurations",
      "prompt": "Given the clue, name the president who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the first president to be inaugurated",
          "answer": "George Washington"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inaugurated two weeks after the U.S. Capitol was stormed by supporters of his predecessor",
          "answer": "Joseph \"Joe\" Biden, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Died thirty days into his term after catching pneumonia during his inauguration",
          "answer": "William Henry Harrison"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the latest president not to attend his successor’s inauguration",
          "answer": "Donald Trump"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the outgoing president who did not attend the inauguration of Ulysses S. Grant",
          "answer": "Andrew Johnson"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was inaugurated minutes before the end of the Iran hostage crisis.",
          "answer": "Ronald Reagan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Started a tradition of walking to the Capitol on inauguration day",
          "answer": "Jimmy Carter"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first president to be inaugurated in Washington, D.C",
          "answer": "Thomas Jefferson 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1 Belgium"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Belgium, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding belgium, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Status of not picking a side which Belgium was required to maintain under the Treaty of London",
          "answer": [
            "Neutral",
            "neutrality"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Capital city that serves as the administrative center of the European Union",
          "answer": "Brussels"
        },
        {
          "question": "Small neighbor nation of which the French-speaking part was ceded to Belgium after the 1839 revolution",
          "answer": "Grand Duchy of Luxembourg"
        },
        {
          "question": "1885 conference formalizing the Scramble for Africa in which Belgium participated",
          "answer": [
            "Berlin Conference",
            "West Africa Conference",
            "Congo Conference"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "King who, once in control of the Congo Free State, ordered his Force Publique to cut off workers' hands",
          "answer": "Leopold II"
        },
        {
          "question": "Post-World War Two multinational organization formed by the 1951 Treaty of Paris of which Belgium was a founding member",
          "answer": [
            "European Coal and Steel Community",
            "ECSC"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Nationalistic opera by Daniel Auber which helped spark its 1830 revolution",
          "answer": [
            "The Mute Girl of Portici",
            "The Dumb Girl of Portici",
            "La muette de Portici",
            "Masaniello"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Political crisis that forced a king of Belgium to abdicate for allegedly working with Nazi Germany",
          "answer": [
            "The Royal Question",
            "Question royale",
            "Koningskwestie 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1 Indira Gandhi"
          ]
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Regarding Indira Gandhi, name the...",
      "prompt": "Name the regarding indira gandhi, name the......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Country she led for over a decade.",
          "answer": "Republic of India"
        },
        {
          "question": "Politician, her father, who was the first prime minister of that country",
          "answer": [
            "Jawaharlal Nehru",
            "Pandit Nehru",
            "Chacha Nehru"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "21-month period of martial law she pushed through in 1975",
          "answer": "The Emergency"
        },
        {
          "question": "Son of hers who oversaw forced sterilizations and died in a plane crash in 1980",
          "answer": "Sanjay Gandhi"
        },
        {
          "question": "Political party led by Morarji Desai which was formed to oppose her",
          "answer": [
            "Janata Party",
            "People's Party"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "President she convinced to invoke Article 352 of the Constitution who died in office in 1977 due to a heart attack",
          "answer": "Fakhruddin Ali Ahmed"
        },
        {
          "question": "Memorials to Indira and her father are located near this memorial in Delhi dedicated to Mahatma Gandhi",
          "answer": "Raj Ghat"
        },
        {
          "question": "English actor and filmmaker who was supposed to interview her the day she was assassinated",
          "answer": "Peter Ustinov 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This country's government laid out the human research principles of \"respect for persons, beneficence, and justice\" in the Belmont Report. Researchers from this country took the HeLa [[HEE-LAH]] cell line from a woman from this country without her consent. From 1932 to 1972, researchers in this nation allowed impoverished (20 pts)",
        "Black men to go untreated from syphilis. This country's intelligence agency carried out mind control experiments as part of Project (10 pts)",
        "MK-Ultra. For ten points, name this country in which the unethical Tuskegee Studies were carried out in Alabama."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United States of America or USA",
        "America"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A ruler of this empire named Alexander died of exhaustion after playing tzykanisterion [[tzik-an-ih-STEER-ee-on]], a form of polo. This empire was defended by strongholds called al-thughur [[al THOO-goor]] between it and the (20 pts)",
        "Umayyads and Abbasids. This empire faced Leo of Tripoli's sack while \"Oleg the Prophet\" attacked its capital, leading to a 911 treaty with the Rus. (10 pts)",
        "Leo VI the Wise and Basil the Bulgar-Slayer ruled, for ten points, what empire from Constantinople?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Byzantine Empire",
        "Byzantines",
        "Eastern Roman Empire",
        "do not",
        "or"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) One band from this country helped popularize distortion in rock music when they sliced their amp with a razor to record the song \"You Really Got Me.\" While performing in Des Moines, Iowa, one musician from this country (20 pts)",
        "bit off the head of a dead bat. Another musician from this country was assassinated by Mark David Chapman. Bands from this country such as The Kinks were part of a 1960s (10 pts)",
        "\"Invasion\" from this country to the United States. For ten points, name this country, home to rock bands such as Black Sabbath, The Rolling Stones, and the Beatles."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "United Kingdom or UK",
        "Great Britain",
        "England"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A classic image of this figure may have been modeled on a photo of Naomi Parker which has been misattributed as Geraldine Hoff. J. Howard Miller was hired to create that image of this figure for (20 pts)",
        "Westinghouse Electric. Based on actual people working in historically male-dominated jobs, much like \"Wendy the Welder,\" this figure was depicted wearing a (10 pts)",
        "red bandana and flexing her arm in a poster which read \"We Can Do It!\" Norman Rockwell popularized, for ten points, what female icon, modeled on real factory workers during World War Two?"
      ],
      "answer": "Rosie the Riveter 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Isamu Nogachi's sculpture Floor Frame is displayed in this building's garden, making him the first artist of Asian lineage to be exhibited here. Childe Hassam's painting The Avenue in the Rain is displayed in this building. James McNeill Whistler and Thomas Jeckyll collaborated on the (20 pts)",
        "Peacock Room in this building. An enslaved person rescued the Lansdowne portrait from this building during the (10 pts)",
        "War of 1812. For ten points, name this building in Washington, D.C., whose decoration has historically been overseen by the First Lady."
      ],
      "answer": "White House"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) States surrounding this one were called Limitrophe [[LEE-meh-trohf]] states which formed the cordon sanitaire [[kor-DONH sahn-ee-TEHR]]. Territorial parts of this country underwent \"korenization.\" Winston Churchill (20 pts)",
        "handed over political control of satellite states to this country in his Mediterranean Strategy, via the Percentages Agreement which left Greece to the Western allies while forsaking (10 pts)",
        "Bulgaria and Romania to communism. For ten points, name this country which was led by Josef Stalin."
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Union of Soviet Socialist Republics",
        "Soviet Union"
      ]
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man led a battalion in a desperate attempt to break Gordon Drummond’s line during the 1814 Battle of Lundy’s Lane, where this man's leadership showed that the U.S. had a truly professional army. This general had his orders disobeyed by future (20 pts)",
        "electoral opponent Franklin Pierce during the Battle of Churubusco [[choo- roo-BOO-skoh]]. This general captured both (10 pts)",
        "Veracruz and Mexico City during the Mexican-American War and was nicknamed \"Old Fuss n' Feathers.\" For ten points, name this 1852 Whig presidential candidate, a general who formulated the Anaconda Plan."
      ],
      "answer": "Winfield Scott"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) British forces captured Mahmoud Fehmy in this country and attacked their opponents at Kassassin. Prince Arthur, the son of Queen Victoria, led a bayonet charge under Garnet Wolseley's command in this country for which William Marsh Edwards won a Victoria Cross. This country, the site of the Battle of (20 pts)",
        "Tel El Kebir, was the location of Richard Eve's defense of Ahmed 'Urabi. In 1919, Saad Zaghlul led this country's Wafd party to rebel. Once governed by (10 pts)",
        "Muhammad Ali, for ten points, what is this country, considered geographically to be in both Africa and Asia?"
      ],
      "answer": [
        "Arab Republic of Egypt",
        "Khedivate of Egypt",
        "Sultanate of Egypt",
        "Ottoman Egypt 2020-21 A-Set History Bowl - 2021-03-03 A Set Bowl - Round 1"
      ]
    }
  ]
}